Previously we used "git checkout" together with the name of the branch, like "master" or "feature".
But technically we can just switch to any commit.
For example, this one [1913].
One can use it to temporary get back to any previous state of the project.
It doesn't matter if any branch is pointing to it or not.
But this creates a so-called "detached HEAD" state.
And we have to understand what is it exactly to avoid doing anything we can regret.
Running...
Wow, git wrote so much about it.
Checkout to commit, actually goes as usual.
Git moves the "HEAD" and updates the files of the project to this commits state.
But theres one thing that git is warning us about with this long message.
The general idea is that we switched into a special state,
that is called "detached HEAD" so the HEAD is not pointing to any branch now.
Previously we gave a branch name to "checkout" command and it switched HEAD to it.
And now we gave it a commit identifier and checkout moved HEAD to it.
In other words HEAD is not pointing to a branch, but to this particular commit instead.
Lets even have a look at a file...
You see, we used to have a branch there and now its a commit identifier.
Namely this is a state called "detached HEAD" and git is warning us about it.
Whats so special about this state and why one should be warned about it?
To understand this lets add one more commit to the project.
Lets change this phrase...
And save the changes into the repo.
Parent of the new commit becomes the one, to which the HEAD was pointing previously -
therefore we get the following image.
If we continue the development, then this commit will have a new one and so one.
These commits pecularity is that they are not a part of any of the branches.
Practically its quite unuseful.
For example, lets switch to the "fix" branch.
Note, that are not in "detached HEAD" state any more, now we are back to the normal branch as before.
And commits that we've done are hanging there,
as they are not a part of any of the branches its even hard to get back to them.
How to actually do that? By commit identifier? Its easy to forget.
Even more, we'll see in one of the next issues that
git can delete this kind of unreachable commits after a while
The situation is kind of dangerous, we dont want to lose the work done so far.
Therefore git warns us about that with this message.
Also it gives us a hint on how to avoid this kind of problems, by creating a branch for these new commits.
From the other side you only make commits being in "detached HEAD" state by mistake.
For example when we switch to commit, instead of just have a look at the state of the project at that time
Then we've checked the project through, forgot that we are in the "detached HEAD" state and made a commit.
While we wanted to commit to the "master" or to the "feature".
Fortunately enough its easy to fix. Git has a cherry-pick command,
that can be given a commit or several commits
and it will copy them to the branch given, like if we made the commits being in this branch
After that the problem is solved.
We'll talk more about the "cherry-pick" command in another issue of the screencast.